# Roman Kharkovski

Pittsburgh, PA, USA

+1-412-267-7662 | kharkovski@gmail.com | LinkedIn | Calendar | Resume | Blog

# TL;DR

Experienced software professional with proven technical aptitude in architecture, software development, analytical, product planning, and sales skills. Combines superior technical and business aptitude. Excellent written and oral communication skills. Team player, leader, deep thinker, works hard, gets things done.

Led technical teams and personally designed, developed and deployed cloud native scalable and secure solutions, traditional on-prem software systems, provided technical leadership, mentoring and training within Google and IBM to engineers, technical sellers, and sales teams. Advised CxO level executives and their staff, as well as engineers within hundreds of Fortune 500 and small companies on IT technical strategy, software and system architecture, software development, SRE and security best practices, machine learning and Al. Earlier in career was a full time software engineer and architected, developed and deployed three-, two- and single-tier applications. Certified Professional Google Cloud Architect, Developer, and Data Engineer.

# **Key Skills**

- Leadership: technical leadership, mentoring, training, complex project and engagement management.
- Google Cloud Platform: building solutions using Cloud Run, GCE, Anthos, GKE, GCS, BigQuery, Cloud Build, IAM, PubSub, App Engine, TimeSeries Insights API, Firestore, BigTable, DataFlow, DataStudio, Workspace (GSuite), Vertex AI, AutoML, Looker, and other GCP services.
- Architecture and DevOps: design and implementation of cloud native, microservices, and traditional on-prem architectures, SRE practices, CICD, containers, VMs, serverless, cost optimization, app migration, and security.
- **Programming:** Python, Java, shell scripting, JavaScript, SQL, C/C++, Lua.
- **JEE:** WebSphere Application Server, JBoss, WebLogic, Tomcat, Jetty, and GlassFish.
- Enterprise integration and messaging: IBM Integration Bus (Message Broker), IBM MQ, Apache ActiveMQ, RabbitMQ, Oracle Service Bus.
- Software competitive research: software performance benchmarking, tested scalability, high availability, development productivity testing, management, security of Java Application Servers, Messaging Middleware, Enterprise Service Bus products and PaaS platforms.
- **Technical sales skills:** IT strategy and solution design, development and delivery of demos and POCs, whiteboarding, negotiation, development of RFP/RFI responses, customer relationships.
- Written and oral communication skills: one of the lead software evangelists for IBM WebSphere brand. Authored 160+ white papers, demos, presentations, text and video <u>blog posts</u>. Presented at hundreds of briefings and conferences in 25 countries reaching an audience of 100,000+ people.
- **Business modeling skills:** designed and implemented several TCO tools for middleware and cloud for use within Google and IBM, extensively used those tools in technical sales engagements.

# **Work Experience**

#### Qarik, Pittsburgh, PA - Principal Architect

April 2023 – present

Helping companies to run their business applications on top of Google Cloud in the most secure, reliable, and efficient way, while making IT staff happier and more productive. Assisting Qarik customers with migration from on-prem and other clouds to GCP, as well as building new cloud native applications.

#### Google, Pittsburgh, PA - TSE, Principal Solution Architect, Google Cloud Platform

October 2021 – March 2023

Leading a team of Solution Architects to design, develop, and deploy two industry solutions for manufacturing: 1) Anomaly Detection, and 2) Intelligent Products. Solutions are an implementation of GCP best practices and shipped to customers with source code, documentation, architecture recommendations, APIs, UI, and Looker dashboards. Collected customer requirements, completed market analysis, created a Solution Requirements Document, Technical Design Document, selected implementation frameworks and toolchain for scalability, security, maintainability, implemented the design in code, including business logic, APIs, persistence, release process and CICD pipeline, command line tools, documentation, developed deployment automation (Cloud Build and Terraform), helped customers deploy solutions into production, operate the solution. Led pilot deployments of the solution in customer owned GCP projects, presented at the HANNOVER MESSE conference.

Created and led an internal community of Solution Architects to promote architecture patterns and code reuse, share experience and lessons learned. Contributed code to an industry solution project template.

#### Google, Pittsburgh, PA - Customer Engineer, Google Cloud Platform

March 2017 – September 2021

Acted as the critical link between customers, sales, product management, partners, and work to implement solutions and resolve technical challenges. Responsible for overseeing the technical integration, platform adoption, and optimization of critical customer projects from start to finish. Drove new business opportunities for the Google Cloud Platform. Built and delivered demonstrations, best practice recommendations, tutorials, technical presentations, cost models, identified new product features and gaps, provided guidance on existing product issues.

Built dozens of customer pilots, and demos for customers in various industries.

Created Open Source hackathon and led a team of engineers to develop <u>Cloud Derby self-driving robot</u> and ran it worldwide for over 1000 participants over multiple Google conferences and customer events.

Created an MVP of a multiplayer "cloud for dummies" educational game <u>KubeDerby</u>.

Created "unofficial" automated Anthos VMware and Anthos AWS installer.

Created other internal Google Source projects and prototypes, including the first Google demo of AutoML for the HIMSS conference for skin condition detection and pill detection.

Created a "Technical School" for GCP sellers and engineers and presented personally and invited speakers to weekly sessions to train the Google North America sales team.

Assisted customers with troubleshooting of their GCP environments, refactoring systems and code to improve scalability, performance, security, and reduce development and deployment time for projects.

# IBM, Pittsburgh, PA - Technical Lead, Worldwide Cloud and WebSphere Competitive Team July 1999 – March 2017

Worldwide leader for competitive research and technical sales in the areas of traditional Middleware and Cloud comparing IBM products to Oracle, Red Hat, Pivotal, Apache, and other commercial and Open Source competitors. Carried out competitive analysis of Java Application Servers, Messaging Middleware, Enterprise Service Bus products. This included performance benchmarking, tests of developer productivity, high availability, reliability, monitoring, and administration. Used technical research findings to build TCO models.

Published 160+ white papers, articles, demos, presentations and videos on the competitive blog.

Worked with over 500 customers to architect applications using best practices of cloud, SOA, OLTP, and microservices: American Express, American Airlines, UPS, Thomson Reuters, State Street, JPMC, USDA, Amdocs, Citicorp, VISA, Mastercard, Geico, Fidelity, Cigna, Lenovo, China Telecom, ADP, Target, Bank of China, US Government, USPS, CVS, Macy's and many others.

Served as technical advisor to IBM executives, product management and development leads, helped define technical roadmaps and go-to-market strategies for WebSphere products.

Worked across sales, marketing, development, and product management in IBM and with Business Partners to plan, fund, coordinate and execute strategic initiatives. Led teams of developers and architects on several software competitive research projects.

Developed and delivered worldwide IBM sales and technical sales competitive enablement and maintained an extensive library of competitive technical and sales collateral.

As a Team Lead for Worldwide WebSphere Team, responsible for hiring and mentoring new talent.

Hands on experience with a wide range of technologies: Service Oriented Architecture, Java EE, microservices, serverless, event driven architecture, cloud, OLTP, Object Oriented design and development, web application design, Web services, SOAP, BPEL, Docker, HTTP, REST, JMS, JPA, Servlets, HTML, XML, DNS, Shell scripts, Linux, Windows, etc.

# Transarc (acquired by IBM), Pittsburgh, PA - Systems Engineer

January 1999 – July 1999

Worldwide technical sales support for WebSphere Application Server.

#### Lanit, Moscow, Russia - Chief Architect & Lead Developer

October 1995 – January 1999

Created the idea, designed, led a small team of developers, and deployed into production the project "Archival Server" for the Central Bank of Russia. The project solved the need to archive, retain and search vast amounts of bank documents on a hierarchical storage system of disks and tapes. (The APIs and spirit of the system is remarkably similar to the modern object storage, such as Google Cloud Storage, AWS S3, etc.) Coded 80% of server software in C, including database schema design and transactional XA services using TUXEDO, Oracle and Informix, AIX, HP-UX.

#### Business Consulting Group, Moscow, Russia - Software Analyst and Developer

September 1994 – October 1995

Architected and developed accounting software for a private mutual fund as well as a retail store automation solution. Used Clarion, Assembler, MS DOS and Novell Netware.

#### Moscow Engineering Physics University, Moscow, Russia - Software Developer

April 1991 – September 1994

Led a team of 5 people to develop and deploy educational software used for undergraduate mathematical optimization classes. Used Borland Object Oriented Pascal, MS DOS.

# **Education**

#### National Research Nuclear University MEPhl (Moscow Engineering Physics Institute, Russia)

September 1989 - February 1995

MS Computer Science, Major - Artificial Intelligence, Minor - Databases.

# **Certifications**

- Google Cloud Professional Data Engineer
- Google Cloud Professional Cloud Developer
- Google Cloud Professional Cloud Architect
- IBM Technical Specialist Profession Certification Level 3 Thought Leader

### **Publications**

#### Some of the Open Source projects

Self driving robot

Training log replicator for USAT Winter Competition

Performance benchmark for MOM

WebSphere MQ automated installer

WebSphere MQ performance bench on Docker

WebSphere Liberty Docker Autoscaler

#### IBM Advantage Blog

Published over 160 articles, white papers, presentations, demos, videos on the blog <u>WhyWebSphere</u>. The blog and its predecessor have more than half a million page views and 1,700+ followers.

#### Book: Migrating Applications from WebLogic, JBoss and Tomcat to WebSphere V6

<u>Book</u> provides detailed information to help plan migrations, best practices for developing portable applications, and working examples for JBoss, Tomcat, WebLogic to WebSphere Application Server.

### **Awards**

- Recipient of dozens of Google Peer and Executive awards, including "Mid Atlantic Jedi CE" in 2017.
- Dozens of IBM awards, including "Outstanding Technical Achievement Award" from IBM CEO.

# **Other**

- Languages: English fluent, Russian native.
- Endorsement and References can be found here